Florence Woolsey Hazzard Papers, 1940-1950
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Florence Hazzard papers
1940-1950
Hazzard, Florence Woolsey, 1903-1992
MS 76
1 box ( .25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Author; Historian. Asmall collection of historian essays on women's history and famous women: Abigail Adams, Susan B. Anthony, Elizabeth Blackwell, Lucy Stone, Emma Willard, Lydia M. Child, Lucretia Mott, Margaret Fuller Ossoli, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, and the Grimke sisters. There is also correspondence from Lucy Elmina Anthony (1940-41).
Historian Florence Woolsey was born in 1903. She received an AB from Goucher College and a Ph.D in Psychology from Cornell University in 1929. At Cornell, she married her high school and graduate school classmate, Albert S. Hazzard. Though she regarded raising her five children her chief occupation and history only a pastime, she went on to become an amateur historian in American women's history. At the University of Washington she was a Research Associate in Women's Studies. She received a Pi Lambda Theta Ella Dobbs award for her manuscript, "Women Pioneers in Democracy," written during a Goucher College fellowship at the University of Michigan in 1948. A digest version was published in the Pi Lambda Theta Journal (Vol. XXVII, No. 2, Part 1, December, 1949). Florence Hazzard died in 1992.
This small collection of historian Florence Hazzard's papers includes primarily manuscript material for her work "Women Pioneers in Democracy" (1948), a series of biographical essays on Abigail Adams, Susan B. Anthony, Elizabeth Blackwell, Lucy Stone, Emma Willard, Lydia M. Child, Lucretia Mott, Margaret Fuller Ossoli, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, and the Grimke sisters. The collection also includes a small amount of biographical material about Hazzard, award letters for her writings (including a letter from Mary Ritter Beard), and correspondence from Lucy Elmina Anthony (niece of Susan B. Anthony).
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Florence Hazzard donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1965 and 1969.
Adams, Abigail, 1744-1818; Anthony, Lucy Elmina; Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906; Blackwell, Elizabeth, 1821-1910; Child, Lydia Maria Francis, 1802-1880; Fuller, Margaret, 1810-1850; Grimke, Angelina Emily, 1805-1879; Grimke, Sarah Moore, 1792-1873; Hazzard, Florence, 1903-1992; Mott, Lucretia, 1793-1880; Stanton, Elizabeth Cady, 1815-1902; Stone, Lucy, 1818-1893; Willard, Emma, 1787-1870; Women's rights-United States-History-Sources; Feminists-United States-Biography-Sources
Additional papers of Florence Woolsey Hazzard are at Cornell University Library, Harvard University (Schlesinger Library), and the New York State Archives.
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Midwestern Writers' Conference: award letter, certificate, and clippings, 1949-51 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Pi Lambda Theta Ella Dobbs Award: article and correspondence (includes Mary R. Beard), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Pioneer Women of Washtenaw County," article by Florence Hazzard, Washtenaw Impressions (Vol. VIII, No. 2, Ann Arbor, MI, Jan 1950) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence with Lucy Elmina Anthony, 1940-41 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Women Pioneers in Democracy": complete unpublished manuscript (1948) with correspondence and notes from editor, acknowledgements, and essays: Abigail Smith Adams, Emma Willard, Lydia Maria Child, Lucretia Mott, The Grimke sisters, Margaret Fuller Ossoli, Elizabeth Blackwell, Lucy Stone, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, and Susan B. Anthony. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous draft essays and notes (includes different versions of essays in "Women Pioneers in Democracy") (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - "The Girls' Declaration of Independence" (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Elizabeth Blackwell, 1821-1910 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Abigail Smith Adams, 1744-1818 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Susan Bromwell Anthony, 1820-1906 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Emma Willard, 1787-1870 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Lydia Maria Child (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Lucretia Coffin Mott (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Grimké Sisters (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Margaret Fuller Ossoli (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Elizabeth Cady Stanton (Box 1, Folder 7-8)